Never forget why you are the church.
If you happen, Lord, say amen.
They're going to have to do that one again, amen?
So, potentially for invitation, I'm not sure.
We'll see how God works that out.
But anyway, um, this morning, I
want you to turn your Bibles to Romans chapter 9.
Romans chapter 9, we're going to continue right
along in our study of Paul's letter to the Romans,
and we have thus far studied several difficult passages.
passages in regard to those who reject him, being
without excuse and given over in chapter one,
the impartiality of God in chapter 2,
the universal and individual guiltiness
of the world in chapter 3, the doctrine
of justification in chapters 4 and 5, the careful
balance between God's grace and sin in our
life in chapter 6, conflict of our 2 natures
in chapter 7.
And last week we finished up chapter 8, exposing a doctrine
and the meaning of God's purpose, and how we can
never be separated from his love.
If you are wondering why it's taken so long in this study,
that's why, amen, you don't just brush past those kind of topics,
you got to really dig deep into what Paul is saying.
But now, understand Paul is not feeding us milk here.
This is the meat of the word, not to be rushed through or
overlooked, and here in starting in chapter 9.
Paul goes through a run of scripture and text,
really flowing from chapters 9 to chapters 11,
with the context and audience pointed towards the Jewish people.
Many directly or strictly and exclusively
direct this text towards the doctrine of salvation.
They see chapter 9, especially as proving a reformed
perspective of election, and if not careful,
it is easy to read it as just that.
However, remember who Paul is speaking to about here?
He is speaking specifically to the Jewish people.
This does not mean that we cannot gain applicable truth for
our daily walk with Christ.
I want you to know there's always something for us in God's word.
Amen?
Listen, if you have ever read God's word and say, what is there for me?
Read it again.
Because you missed it.
So we're going to buckle up and put our thinking caps on.
There will be much teaching throughout these 3 chapters.
I do not want to, I do not want to,
you know, make it to where it's not preachy, but I really want to get
down to the nitty gritty and the details.
But I do want to preface this portion of sermons with some words of the apostle Peter.
In 2nd Peter chapter 3, verse 14 and 18,
Peter says this, wherefore, beloved, seeing
that she look for such things, be diligent, that
she may be found of him in peace without spot and blameless.
An account that the long suffering of our Lord is salvation,
even as our beloved brother, Paul, also,
according to the wisdom given unto him, hath written unto you,
as also in all his epistles, speaking in them of these things.
Now, here's what he says, in which are some
things hard to be understood.
Which they that are unlearned in unstable rest as they do,
also the other scriptures unto their own destruction.
Ye therefore, beloved, seeing ye know these things before,
beware, lest ye also being led away with the error of the wicked,
far from your own steadfastness, but
growing grace, and in the knowledge of our Lord and Savior,
Jesus Christ, to him, be glory both now and forever.
Amen.
You're saying, what in the world does why would you bring that up?
Because Peter, would you consider Peter pretty knowledgeable
about the things of God?
Pretty, I mean, you know, pretty just led the church
in Jerusalem, you know what I'm saying?
He walked with Christ himself.
He himself says, man, some things that Paul writes are hard to understand.
Y'all with me?
What I'm trying to say is this.
There's some things we're not going to fully understand.
And I can preach message after message after message.
And let me just tell you something.
I try.
My best.
When I'm in my office, when I'm in my study.
I'm sitting, I want to give answers.
And I want to give them clearly and directly.
And that's what we're going to try to do, but I want you just to know, some
things are just hard to understand.
How many people have taken a tough
text in God's word?
And in trying to understand it, in
the way they can understand it, have walked
in error of the way.
We're not going to do that here, Cedar Grove.
Amen?
Are y'all with me?
So let's look at God's word with humility rather
than a hottie spirit.
Today I was planning on reading the entire chapter of Romans 9 to you.
And then I change my mind.
So someone say, thank you, preacher.
Yeah, the slot girls.
They're like, thank you so much.
But what I do want to challenge you is this.
I want you to go home today, okay, before you get all busy tomorrow.
And I want you to read chapter nine, okay?
Because what's going to happen is as you read chapter 9,
you're going to realize, whoa, this is where that is.
And whoa, okay, I've heard of this.
And man, I got a question about that.
And I hope that as we go through this chapter 9, 10, and 11.
We will get some answers as we can.
So we're going to be in Romans chapter 9.
I'm going to read verses one through five.
If you're there, say read.
I say the truth in Christ.
This is Paul speaking.
I lie not.
My conscience also bearing me witness in the Holy Ghost, that
I have great heaviness and continual sorrow in my heart.
For I could wish that myself were accursed from Christ for my brethren.
My kinsmen, according to the flesh, who are the
Israelites, to whom pertaineth the adoption, and the glory,
and the covenants, and the giving of the law, and
the service of God, and the promises, whose
are the fathers, and of whom, as concerning the flesh
Christ came, who is over all, God blessed forever.
Amen.
The title of this text, or as overall,
is going to be called unexplainable mercy, unexplainable mercy.
Let's pray, Father, I thank you for your word.
God, I thank you for just a spirit of readiness to receive today
that I sense God and the people.
So God, I pray, Lord, that you allow me to speak,
God, in this sacred death, God, your word.
God, I pray those that have ears to hear, may they hear.
God give me power, clarity, and wisdom to
do what you've anointed me to do in this time.
God, I pray, Lord, that it is somebody here who's lost, God.
I pray today.
The fact that Jesus lived, died, and rose again.
God, through your drawing and conviction of the Holy Spirit,
I pray today is a day of salvation for him.
And we can celebrate that.
God, show us.
And it's in Jesus name, pray.
And everybody said, Amen.
Paul is writing this with the purpose of answering some important
and relevant questions that were no doubt being asked by believing and doubting Jews.
For example, if you were a Jewish person, you would read
this and it would not be as, it
would be confusing, but not as confounding as it would be for us, because,
see, the Jews understood their history.
In that culture, the culture
we have today, and I feel like it's fading more and more.
We are not caring about our history in America, as we should.
See, the Israelites had no problem with that.
They understood that we are to study what God has done.
And even when they did that, if you look over their history, they
still walked away from him time after time.
But if God had chosen Israel as his nation
and people, why were there so many Jewish people who
had not received Christ as Lord?
As a matter of fact, many unbelieving Jews will use this
as a deterrent away from putting their faith in Jesus.
If the majority of us has not believed, then how can
it be true that Jesus who came was the Messiah?
Again, remember the Jewish culture and knew their history.
They were all looking for the coming Messiah.
This was more of a national deliverance they were looking for
than a personal deliverance, yet they rejected Jesus.
to his face.
I want us to continue this thought process as we go over this chapter.
But this morning, however, I was trying
to see how I can chop this up and make it flow
to where it makes sense and not just preach
for 3 hours every Sunday for the next 3 or 4 Sundays.
So God really just kind of struck
me with the 1st 5 verses.
So I want to really hone in on this particular thought.
Number one, the people of mercy.
I want to read verses one through 5 again, okay?
Look at it.
We going to read it, says this.
I say the truth in Christ, I lie not.
My conscience also bearing me witness in the Holy Ghost, that
I have great heaviness and continual sorrow in my heart.
For I could wish that myself were a curse from Christ, for my brethren,
my kinsmen, according to the flesh, you are the Israelites, to
whom pertaineth the adoption and the glory in the covenants, and the living,
the giving of the law and the service of God, and the promises, whose
are the fathers, and of whom, as concerned the flesh, Christ
came, who is over all, God bless forever.
Amen.
See, Paul here shows how grieved
he is personally about this rejection
of Jesus by his fellow Israelites.
Literally, he explains this grief as a great heaviness
and continual sorrow in his heart.
He writes one of the most harrowing statements from any of
the apostles that I, I think we could read.
And he says this, for I wish that myself were accursed from Christ.
For my brethren, my kinsmen according to the flesh.
See, we read that and we think, okay, that's cool.
That's preacher talking, man, Paul is so spiritual.
I don't think we understand the weight and intensity
of what Paul was saying.
The significance of what he just declared, that word
accursed is the Greek word anathema.
It means obviously one who is cursed, but a
deeper look at the word means separation from Christ.
Paul has used this word in other letters.
1 Corinthians 16,22.
If any man love not the Lord, Jesus Christ, let him, Anathema, Maranatha.
Galatians one, 8 through nine, but though we or
an angel from heaven preach any other gospel unto you, then that
which we have preached unto you, let him be accursed, the same word.
As we said before, so say I now, again, if any man preach any
other gospel unto you than that ye have received, let him be accursed.
Even though impossible, Paul is so hurt, so greed
by his kinsmen, rejecting Jesus that he
offers himself for hell in their place.
I couldn't imagine such a hurt.
Now, the reason why this struck me.
I want to take a moment to point inward today for everyone here.
What kind of heart do you have for the lost?
I mean, I want to really think about it.
Do we even come close to the heaviness and
sorrow, Paul declares here in Romans nine?
Does the lostness of our loved ones, our family,
our friends, does it truly hurt us?
Well, preacher, are we supposed to just walk around sorrowing
all day for those who reject Christ?
I mean, we wouldn't be able to do anything but cry and weep.
That's not what I'm saying necessarily, but we are to pray for
them, to proclaim the gospel, to them, to
teach them and show them Jesus.
That is why we're here on this earth.
By the way, I want you to know what causes the most sorrow in
your heart is what you care about the most.
So many of us can look at ESPN
app and see that our team lost and we can sit there for
hours on end bothered and irritated because a
team lost, but we can read in the paper that a
friend from our childhood that we don't know if they know Christ, we
just know that they were rejecting Christ.
William and you, him.
They died and possibly in hell.
We just keep on reading.
Do we care?
What causes the most sorrow in your heart is
what you care the most about.
I tell you what we aren't supposed to do as believers.
get used to their lostness.
See, Paul was deeply hurt seeing the people he loved reject
Christ, so what did he do?
That motivated him to what?
Stay on mission.
He understood that every single day that he woke up, that
the majority of his kinsmen, the majority of the people that
he loved was rejecting Christ, and if they died that day, they were go to hell.
By the way, what did Jesus say about it?
Well, Matthew 9, 37 through 38, then saith
he unto his disciples, the harvest truly is
plenteous, but the laborers are few.
Pray ye, therefore, the Lord of the harvest, that he will send
forth laborers into his harvest.
You do realize why we're gathering here today to
send out laborers into the harvest.
But what we turn this into so often is a little clubhouse
setting mating of, hey, let's get together with our people.
Let's shake hands.
Let's dress up a little bit.
Let's listen to our favorite songs.
Let's do this, let's do that.
But we go out there, and we just wait till Sunday.
This isn't just going to church or attending revival or VBS.
All those things are good.
This is a call to action, to get out into the world
and labor to see the law saved.
People laugh all the time about my sauna jokes.
For the guests that are here, if you haven't heard already.
We are fully clothed in the sauna that I go to.
That's evidently a thing.
I don't know.
But not a sports village, okay?
But either way, listen, and people say, why do you talk about it so much?
Because I go to a sauna for health, right?
I don't, you know, heart disease, all things, whatever it says in the little sheet,
I'm like, man, I hope that's true.
You know, back in the day, they're like, hey, tanning bed's good for you.
Then they say, oh, tanner bed's terrible for you.
Then you're like, what is true?
But either way, so I go into the sauna, but I go in intentionally.
I actually, and this is just one part.
I'm not trying.
trying to sit there and say that I got it understanding, but I understand this.
I go in, and I know for a fact that
all we're doing for the next 15 or 20 minutes is sitting
in that heat and sweating it out, and in my mind, I'm
thinking, there's no way I'm not gonna say something about Jesus to
these people in this sauna right now.
Now, again, it's, by the way, I might do a podcast one day, and
it might be the sauna conversations, Joe.
That's a good one.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
I mean, you know, I don't know how that would work with the equipment,
but either way, get the preacher in the sauna,
and I get the question of why they're sweating.
You know, that'd be awesome.
Anyway, let's go back to what we were talking about.
But no, I have an intentionality.
As a matter of fact, when I pass when I pass by,
before I go in,
And again, I know this is a silly illustration.
But when I pass by, when I go in, I get upset when there's no one in there.
That's one part of my life that I am the most intentional about to sow win.
Now, you say, well, preacher, you should be more intentional on that.
I'm just letting you know, that's one part.
And can I tell you something?
You know how many conversations I've had with people.
I say, hey man, you go to church anywhere.
That's the Southern Bible Belt way to start the conversation.
You know what I'm saying?
You go to church anywhere.
Ah, yeah, I go to church, I go to this church.
Cool.
I don't go to church.
That's not for me.
That's cool.
It's for me.
want to talk about it.
All we're doing is sit, you say, that's so dumb.
Where is that in your life?
Well, I don't have time.
I don't have this.
I don't have that.
You do realize Paul and scriptures.
He talks about the fact that he had a job.
He worked.
He worked and had to make money to eat and all the things and he
did all that while planting churches, while discipling
young men for the Lord, while teaching doctrine and teaching scripture.
He did all these things while leading whole towns to Christ.
He did all that while having another schedule as well.
He was just on mission.
His priority was straight.
Jesus does not give us an excuse.
As a matter of fact, when Jesus was opening the understanding of
the disciples after his resurrection before his ascension, what did he say?
Look at Luke chapter 24 on the screen,
verses 46 to 49.
And he said unto them, thus it is written, and thus it behoved
Christ to suffer and to rise from the dead the 3rd day, and
that repentance and remission of sins should be preached in
his name among all nations, beginning at Jerusalem.
And you are witnesses of these things.
And behold, I send the promise of my Father upon you, but
tarry ye in the city of Jerusalem until you be endued
with power from on high.
We see that power spoken about again in Acts chapter one, verse 7, 8.
And he said unto them, it is not for you to know the times of the seasons,
which the Father had put in his own power, but you shall
receive power after that the Holy Ghost has come upon
you, and ye shall be witnesses unto me both in Jerusalem,
and in all Judea, and Samaria, and unto the uttermost part of the earth.
When did that power come?
Well, we saw the day of Pentecost.
Again, we're going to keep on reading Acts chapter 2, verse one through five.
And when the day of Pentecost was fully come, they were all with one accord and one place.
By the way, I wonder if we were all in one accord
and one place what God could do with Cedar Grove.
I might preach another message right now.
I wonder if we were just all in one accord,
that means singleness of heart, soul, and mind.
And in one place, the power that we could experience.
Hmm.
And suddenly there came a sound from heaven as of a rushing mighty
wind, and it filled all the house where they were sitting.
And there appeared unto them, cloven tongues like as a fire, and
it sat upon each of them, and they were all filled with the Holy Ghost, and
began to speak with other tongues as the Spirit gave them utterance.
And there were dwelling at Jerusalem, Jews devout men.
One of every nation under heaven.
You say, man, that is so cool.
They were filled with the power of the Holy Ghost, but why?
What was the purpose of the filling with the power?
What was the power for, to proclaim the life,
death, and burial and resurrection of Jesus Christ, to
speak the truth of Jesus?
By the way, did you know that the same power
that both rose Jesus from the dead and filled those
in the upper room at Pentecost dwells within the
believer today?
If you are born again, if you are saved,
a child of God, a saint, that means that you have this
same power dwelling within you.
Now, the Holy Spirit is God, right?
And God showed that power then, and
we saw what that power could do, but yet
we had that same power, the Holy Ghost dwelling within us,
but yet we're not seeing the power.
Let me tell you something.
It's not God's fault.
It's our fault.
It's our unholy living.
It's our lack of ambition for the things of God.
It's our distraction that we have that thinks
that Christianity is just to be put in 4 walls about
2 hours a week.
No wonder there's no power in the church, even
though we are the most powerful people in the world.
Why do you think this is?
Why do you think God gives us the fruit of the spirit to bear?
Why does the Spirit remind us of what we've been taught?
Why has God given us all things that pertain to life
and godliness?
Church, hear me?
It's not just for our life.
It's not just for our needs.
It's not just for our spiritual wellness.
It's not just to build big churches with fancy buildings,
it's not just to offer program after program and ministry after ministry.
Those are all great, but they are simply a product of the
foundational reason, all these things help the believer
point the unbeliever to Jesus.
We can relate to what Paul says next in many ways.
Romans chapter 9, again, verse 3 through 5, he says this,
for I wish that myself were a curse from Christ, my brethren.
My kids been according to the flesh who are Israelites.
To whom pertaineth the adoption and the glory and the covenants and the giving of
the law and the service of God, and the promises, whose are
their fathers, and of whom as concerning the flesh Christ
came, who is over all God blessed forever, amen.
He states 7 things.
that the Israelite was spiritually privileged with.
Seven things here.
First off, we see the adoption as sons.
The divine glory, the covenants, the
receiving of the law, temple worship, that
is service of God, the promises of God,
the patriarchs.
Yet they rejected Christ.
Church, do you realize that we live in a time where there is a new covenant?
You say, what does that mean?
Whoever calls upon the name of the Lord will be saved.
Now, listen, I believe that they put
their faith in Christ in the Old Testament as well.
But I want you to know something.
We don't need to have a farm in the back to get
forgiven of sins.
We have Jesus.
He still adopts those who desire to be his.
As a matter of fact, he has never not adopted an
orphan who desired to be adopted.
That's good.
His glory is now shown through the risen Savior.
We have open access to the completed word of God,
held right here in our hands.
The most stolen and bought piece of literature
in all of history.
We have churches on every corner by which people can gather
and serve the Lord together.
We have those who have gone before us that paved the way for biblical
exposition and spiritual leadership, but
what about the promises?
And we may not forget 2 Corinthians chapter one, verse
20, for all the promises of God in him that
is Jesus, or yea, and in him, amen,
unto the glory of God, by us.
In other words, all the promises of God and Jesus are yes and amen.
Yet.
How many still reject them?
How many live in the culture we live in?
Where there's church signs on every corner.
There's literature everywhere.
There's resources, there's ministries all over our town.
Yeah, people are so far from God.
Could it be for our lack of heart form?
Pamphlets are good.
Flowers are great.
All these things that we liked.
As a matter of fact, me and River were talking.
It's my five year old daughter, and
we were walking, we went on a walk last night, and,
uh, we were walking past all the houses in our neighborhood, and
she said, she said, remember that time when we went
out and we gave gave out those cards, and we were
like, had those bags, and we were like, knocking on doors, and you would let me
go and give them to the people.
I was like, yeah, I remember that.
We were getting ready for the go tell, um, crusade and stuff.
She said, you said, man, that was fun.
And then she said that she said, When am we going to do that again?
And so, of course, I'm just convicted.
And I said, we didn't do it soon, baby.
But here's the thing.
Could it be that we have traded in a
relational evangelism strategy for just throwing things as
people with people's mailboxes.
Do we think, ah, well, if they want to go to church, they can find one?
Let me ask you something.
When you were lost and far from God,
were you just trying to look for a church or were you looking for the bar and the club?
I mean, did you mistakenly come to Cedar Grove instead of Nashville?
I mean, you see what I'm saying?
Like we expect, we expect lost people to
do what we're only want to do oftentimes.
Are y'all with me this morning?
As I was driving down Cedar Grove Road.
And I really want to bring this to a place of response.
As I was driving down Cedar Grove Road to the church this morning,
I come down this way, obviously, and one
of my favorite views in all of Lebanon is looking out past the
church, and before the neighborhood,
it had like trees, and it would have like, you know, fog and stuff, and
you'd see the trees.
It was just absolutely gorgeous situation.
And I would always just kind of drive slow, you know,
to make sure I took it all in.
But I had a perfect view this morning of the new houses that they
had begun to build just a stone stow away from our church right down there.
And honestly, it's shocking how fast it's happening.
I feel like we're never we never cease to get amazed at how fast they put a house up.
like they had one up and now they're like working on the 4th one.
the craziest thing ever.
And I know most of us are thinking right now.
and it's a good thought.
Man, our church is gonna grow.
I mean, they're putting 100 and something houses right down the road.
Surely we're going to grow and certainly, I
pray that we are able to add families to our families here.
But then as I'm driving, I'll get to thinking some more.
There's plenty of houses already around us who are
homes to people far from God.
Believers who have gotten off the path.
Christians who have been hurt and have left the church.
When is the last time we were excited to share the gospel with them?
Oh, but look at the new houses and it's a new neighborhood
is right down the road, but
Yeah, we have neighbors that are dying going to hell right now.
Again, if you've been here long enough, you know that we are outreach professionals
for four to six weeks.
Y'all with me?
Man, we'll start an outreach program.
We'll start going door to door.
We'll have 16, 20, 25, people show up all
excited, ready to go, get in that van and just attack a neighborhood,
get the police called on us.
I mean, it's just the craziest thing ever.
We're just like running in the front yard.
You need Jesus.
The second week, man, we're just excited.
We going to get ice cream after.
Like, it's just a fun time.
Third week comes, huh?
And by the 5th or 6th week, it's we'll get it next spring.
We fade back into our busy lives again.
Well, reaching out to the community.
and going door to door.
That's the preacher's job.
You show me where that is in scripture, how you just said it, and
we'll have a conversation, but let me just you can't.
Now, I'm not saying a preacher shouldn't do it.
But what I'm saying is that's the problem with the church so often is that we say,
hey, let's get the professional Christians to do the things that every Christian should do.
Could it be that we treat those closest to us who are lost the same way?
We hear a message or someone gets sick or we attend
a funeral that reminds us of the reality of eternity.
And we get all passionate about sharing Jesus just for it to fade out of priority.
A few weeks later.
How many people were all gung ho and excited about
sharing the gospel and being in church after the assassination of Charlie Kirk?
I must be honest with you, I haven't thought about it in weeks.
I'm not trying to disrespect.
I'm just saying that's how easy it is.
to forget those moments that I believe God puts in our life to remind us.
This is why you're here.
I'm thankful God doesn't love us like that.
Loves us for years and years and years, and then out of impatience just lets us go.
By the way, this church will be full to the brim with a need to expand tomorrow
if we would just simply bring those closest to us to Jesus.
Church today, when is the last time you sorrowed over someone's lostness?
When is the last time you had the mindset of whatever it takes in sharing the gospel?
You want to know what it looks like to have the continual heaviness and
sorrow in a heart?
The whatever it takes mindset for Paul says, for I
wish that myself were a curse that is separated from
Christ, my brethren, my kinsmen, according to the flesh, we
can't even separate ourselves from our schedules.
to see those we love come to Jesus.
You say, well, I prayed for them, and they didn't come...
You prayed for him for, what, two weeks?
Well, I shared the gospel with them, and they rejected.
One time?
You know how many messages I sat in lost?
In church, getting preached the gospel to,
yet rejected time and time again, folks, listen, it
may take a 100 times for you to share, but if they come to Christ, it's worth it.
So do we have a heart for the lost?
Do we sorrow for those in our family?
They died right now, they go to hell.
Or It
just is what it is, preacher.
That's not how Jesus saw it.
That's not how Paul sees it.
And I pray to God, that's not how Cedar Grow sees it.
When hezbound eyes close over his place.